Register of the Ethan Theodore Colton papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Subject files, 1917-1934, undated (Box 6-8, 10)
  - USSR, 1928-1934, undated (bulk 1932-1934). (Folder 7: 17-18)
    Includes printed brochure on the YMCA's work to support Christian faith among Russians and provide relief aid. Related: YMCA Press translation correspondence, 1925-1932
  - World revolution, 1922-1932, undated, bulk 1925-1932 (Folder 8: 1-3)
    Includes documents holographically labeled with a roman numeral, for example "Document IV." Also includes series of newspaper articles on Russia by E. Ashmead-Bartlett
  - World revolution, Soviet Russia, and religion, 1924-1929 (bulk 1928-1929) (Folder 8: 4)
    Includes translations holographically marked with edits and date circulated.
- YMCA Press Russian News files, 1924-1935, undated (Box 8-9)
  Consists mainly of numbered typescript translations into English of Russian-language newspaper articles, with some translations of other periodical articles, speeches, and orders of the Soviet government. Includes correspondence, 1924-1932, related to the origin, scope, and operation of the program, and to administration of the translation work. The translations are arranged in their original order, in numerical sequence. Original batches of translations as received from translators are identified as such; otherwise, the translation number range merely represents the range as found in the files. Not all numbered translations in a sequence are present. Some additional numbered translations are found in Colton's Working documents or Subject files. Related: Incremental Materials, October 1987
  - YMCA Press Russian news translations typescript drafts, 1933-1935, undated (Folder 8)
    - Translations numbers 2079-2121, 1933 (Folder 8: 5)
    - Translations numbers 2170-2299, 1933-1934 (Folder 8: 6)
    - Translations numbers 2301-2312, 1934 (Folder 8: 7)
    - Translations numbers 2313-2317, 1933, undated (Folder 8: 8)
    - Translations numbers 2318-2328, 1934 (Folder 8: 9)
    - Translations numbers 2329-2375, 1934 (Folder 8: 10)
      Comprises original entire batch of translations with typescript cover note
    - Translations numbers 2398-2470, 1934 (Folder 8: 11)
    - Translations numbers 2762-2831, 1934-1935 (Folder 8: 12)
      Comprises original entire batch of translations with typescript cover note. Includes translations of articles published 1934 October through 1935 April 29
    - Translations numbers 2832-2937, 1934-1935, undated (Folder 8: 13-14)
      Comprises original entire batch of translations with typescript cover note. Includes translations of articles published through 1935 July
  - YMCA Press Russian news translations typescript drafts incremental materials, 1924-1935. (Folder 9)
    Includes some unnumbered translations
    - 1924-1935 (bulk 1934-1935) (Folder 9: 1-3)
      - Translations numbers 1750, 1836, 1842, 1877, and 2651-2704; unnumbered translations of news articles dated 1932; and typescript summary of results of medical examination of students, 1924, 1924, 1932 (Folder 9: 1)
      - Translations numbers 2938-3000, 1935 (Folder 9: 2)
      - Holographic notes on the inside front of the original folder, undated (Folder 9: 3)
    - 1930-1932 (Folder 9: 4-5)
      - Unnumbered translations of news articles dated 1930, and Translations numbers 1053-1284, 1313, 1321, 1368, 1388, and 1394, 1930-1931 (Folder 9: 4)
      - Translations numbers 1406-1748, 1931-1932 (Folder 9: 5)
    - 1934-1935 (Folder 9: 1-3)
      - Translations numbers 2376-2396, 1934 (Folder 9: 1)
      - Translations numbers 2473-2521, 1934 (Folder 9: 2)
      - Translations numbers 2523-2716, 1934-1935 (Folder 9: 3)
  - YMCA Press Russian news translation correspondence, 1925-1932 (Folder 8)
    - 1925-1930 (bulk 1925-1929) (Folder 8: 5)
    - 1929-1932 (Folder 8: 6)
- Incremental materials, 1987 October (Box 9: 12)
  Consists of ESR reports; YMCA Press Russian News typescript translations; ESR documents Colton labeled Exhibit A, F, and G, relating to proposed continuation of ESR aid; typescript translations and printed material, 1923-1924 and undated